<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The propositions sent by the Irish Parliament held at Kilkenny, to the commissioners at Dublin. / Signed by Lodwick O Bourk Speaker of the House of Parliament at Kilkenny.</title>
            <author>Confederate Catholics. Supreme Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87327</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I641</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E407_31</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E421_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202606</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862834</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862834</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161371</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87327)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161371)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 64:E407[31] or 66:E421[21])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The propositions sent by the Irish Parliament held at Kilkenny, to the commissioners at Dublin. / Signed by Lodwick O Bourk Speaker of the House of Parliament at Kilkenny.</title>
                  <author>Confederate Catholics. Supreme Council.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for I.H. and are to be sold neare the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copies: "7ber [i.e. September] 20th" (407[31]); "Decemb: 31" and "1647" (421[21]).</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  Politics and government --  1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161371:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PROPOSITIONS SENT By the <hi>Jriſh Parliament</hi> held at <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> TO The Commiſsioners AT DUBLIN.</p>
            <p>Signed by <hi>Lodwick O Bourk</hi> Speaker of the Houſe of Parliament in <hi>Kilkenny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed for I. H. and are to be ſold neare the <hi>Royall Exchange,</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proposition">
            <pb facs="tcp:161371:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:161371:2"/>
            <head>PROPOSITIONS SENT By the <hi>Jriſh Parliament</hi> held at <hi>Kilken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> to the Commiſſioners at <hi>Dublin;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Peace in that Kingdome.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough it ſo fortuned by the chance of Warre, that our Forces under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of his Excellency Gen. <hi>Preſton,</hi> at the laſt conflict in the field were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing over-powerd by yours, with the loſſe of ſome of our native Countrimen of ranke and quality, of which we being ſo ſenſible on, cannot but for a time cloath our ſelves in mourning. Yet doth it not any waies diſmay us, or ſtrike us with feare or terrour, nor cauſes us any wayes to deſpaire of the future event of the Warre; but only a ſerious conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and religious care which we have of this our native Kingdome: to prevent the effuſion of Chriſtian bloud, of which there hath been an over-flowing tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent for a long time ſpread over this diſtreſſed and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Kingdome which induceth us to be the firſt, and exemplary inſtruments to revert the gluttonous
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:161371:3"/>Sword from banqueting in bloud and deſtruction, on which for theſe ſeven yeares it hath been feaſted; and to bring it backe again to its former place, to wit, to the hand of the Civill Magiſtrate, to execute temporall Juſtice; and that the antient known Lawes of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome might return to their former place: His Majeſty enjoy his ſupream power and dignity; the Natives to have their liberties as Subjects, and not to be enthralled as ſlaves, that ſo they and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> might again live together as friends and fellow Subjects.</p>
            <p>For the accompliſhing of which, we the confederate Eſtates of the Kingdome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> aſſembled in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament at <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> do deſire that there might be ſo far a complacency between us and you; that the originall and preſent differences betwixt us might be ſo really un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood: whereby we hope by the clearnes of actions preſent, and our future endeavours may be apparent to all, whereby we may make our ſelves quit of that ſcandalous and infamous brand of bloudy Rebels.</p>
            <p>For the obtaining of which, we deſire, that ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient place might be appointed, where a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble number of Nobility and Gentry, both of your Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ours, might have ſome time perfixt to meet, with free commiſſion on both ſides, to treat and conſult to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, that thereby (with Gods aſſiſtance we may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy at length a happy peace and union) and this miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and bleeding Kingdome preſerved from farther ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine and deſolation, which hath ſo long lain weltring in its own gore, and the diſtreſſed inhabitants reſtored to their former peace and plenty.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:161371:3"/>
            <p>But this our reall and ſincere requeſts, ſome may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture may proceed from our cowardly feare, or poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that by this meanes of Treaty, the actions of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies for this Summer might be retarded: but if any do looke upon our Forces at home in Garriſon, and abroad in the field, they will find that we ſtand not in need of ceſſation for want of Forces to keepe the field: and we are confident it is not unknown to moſt of you: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that part of an Army then at <hi>Lniſhknock</hi> with Generall <hi>Preſton</hi> received ſome damage; yet have we an Army in the field, marching under Generall <hi>Owen O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neale,</hi> which were not engaged there, nor elſwhere, ſince their laſt victory at <hi>Blackwater:</hi> which Army (be it ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken without vain glory) is almoſt double the number the men which you have in Armes in this Kingdome: and of their vallours we preſume that the <hi>Scots</hi> and your other Forces in <hi>Ulſter,</hi> can give a ſufficient teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of: yet put the caſe we had not this Army, yet God be praiſed this Kingdome, or at leaſt this part of the Kingdome in our poſſeſſion is not ſo ill ſtor'd with men nor our Magazines with Armes and Ammunition, but we could have recruted Generall <hi>Preſtons</hi> Army with double the number he loſt at <hi>Lniſhknock:</hi> Wherefore yee may clearely ſee, it is not the want of men or am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition that induceth us to Parlee: but if you ſhall find your hearts ſo peaceably inclined as to admit of it, there may be ſuch care taken on both ſides for the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Commiſſioners: and yet no ceſſation of Armes for the Souldier, till the Commiſſioners ſhall conclude and agree thereunto.</p>
            <p>But for the Armies to proceed in any way of hoſtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:161371:4"/>to eithers beſt advantage notwithſtanding the Treaty and yet to be be no prejudice to the Commiſſioners of either ſide.</p>
            <p>We alſo deſire that we might have the ſame priviledge as other his Majeſties Subjects have in the like nature, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſend a convenient number of Commiſſioners, whom we ſhall thinke fit, to <hi>London</hi> or elſwhere in the Kingdome of <hi>England;</hi> and they there to reſide as Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners to communicate the weighty affaires of this Kingdome, both to the Kings Majeſty and to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſes of Parliament there; by which our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons paſt, and our future intentions, may be cleared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the face of the world; and that thoſe blemiſhes may be taken away from us and our poſterities, which ſome are pleaſed to brand us with; and that all men may ſee that our intentions are only for peace and unity, that we and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> may again live lovingly together as friends and fellow Subjects.</p>
            <p>But if you thinke it prejudiciall to you to have any number of Commiſſioners to go for <hi>England;</hi> we ſhall then deſire that only two whom we ſhall appoint, may have a ſafe convoy over for <hi>England,</hi> and ſo back again, to addreſſe themſelves to his Majeſty and to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and there to endeavour the procuring of his Majeſties Royall aſſent, and alſo the conſent of both Houſes of Parliament to ſuch Articles as ſhall be propounded towards the ſettlement of a firme and well grounded Peace in the three Kingdomes; that ſo wee may put a period to theſe miſerable and bloudy diſtractions that hath ſo long attended on
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:161371:4"/>this deplorable Nation. And that his Majeſty with his Royall Conſort, and their Poſterity, may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy their juſt Rights and Royall Prerogatives; and the Subject his juſt Liberties and Freedome.</p>
            <p>Sir this is the deſire of the Lords and Commons aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in the ſupreame councell of this Kingdome, held at <hi>Kilkenny:</hi> And if your honour will be pleaſed to ſend your anſwer, you will engage us to be,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Auguſt</hi> 28. 1647.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Servants, <hi>Lodwick O Bourk,</hi> Speaker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
